centered at C equal 1 so what we need to
in this video we're gonna talk about how
and that's it for this problem so you
to find a Taylor series and the
Maclaurin series for different functions
so let's start with this example let's
find the Taylor series given the
function f of X is equal to Ln X
do is basically write out the first four
derivatives so f prime of X the
derivative of Ln X that's 1 over X now
to find a second derivative we need to
rewrite it and then use the power rule
so the second derivative is negative 1
divided by x squared and then to find
the third derivative let's use the power
rule again so for the third derivative
is going to be 2 divided by X cube event
to find the fourth derivative it's going
to be negative 1 times negative 2 that's
positive 2 and then we need to take the
derivative of X to the negative third
power so that's negative 3 X to the
negative 4 so the fourth derivative is
negative 6 divided by X to the fourth
power
now the next thing that we need to do is
evaluate the function and the
derivatives at C so f of 1 C is one
that's going to be Ln 1 the natural log
of 1 is 0 and then f prime of 1 is going
to be 1 over 1 which is 1 and then the
second derivative evaluated at 1 that's
negative 1 divided by 1 squared which is
just negative 1 and for the third
derivative it's going to be positive 2
and the value for the fourth derivative
when X is 1 is negative 6 divided by 1
to the 4 for simply negative 6 so now we
can get rid of this stuff
now this is the formula that you want to
use to write the expanded form of the
Taylor series so it's F of C plus F
prime of C times X minus C to the first
power plus F double prime of C times X
minus C to the second power divided by 2
factorial plus the third derivative
evaluated at C times X minus C to the
third power divided by 3 factorial and
then it just continues so f of X which
is Ln X we can say that it's equal to F
of C which is F of 1 and we know that F
of 1 is 0 and then plus F prime of C
which is 1 times X minus C C is 1 and
then the second derivative that's going
to be negative 1 so that's f double
prime of C times X minus C to the second
power divided by 2 factorial and then
for the third derivative that's gonna
equal 2 so that's going to be plus 2
times X minus C to the third power
divided by 3 factorial and then we have
negative 6x minus C to the fourth power
divided by 4 factorial and then that's
going to continue
now let's simplify what we have so we
don't need to write a zero so we can say
that the natural log of X is X minus C
to the first power divided by 1
factorial and then minus wanted to get
rid of the seen this is supposed to be X
minus 1 to the first power and then it's
gonna be minus X minus 1 squared divided
by 2 factorial which is simply 2 and
then plus what is 2 divided by 3
factorial 3 factorial is 3 times 2 times
and so we can cancel the 2 so therefore
this is gonna be plus X minus 1 to the
third power divided by 3 I'm just gonna
write this as 1 so you can see the
pattern and then we're gonna have this
is gonna be negative now 6 divided by 4
factorial let's simplify that for factor
is 4 times 3 times 2 times 1 so 6 will
cancel with 3 times 2 so this is gonna
be X minus 1 to the fourth power divided
by 4 so now we could see a pattern
developing so how can we write this
series using summation notation
so let's start with n equals zero and
we're going to go to infinity so when n
is zero we need to get one as an
exponent when n is one we need to get
two and when n is two we need to get
three so therefore it's always one more
than our n value so we're gonna have n
plus one so this is gonna be X minus one
raised to the n plus one power and since
these numbers are the same we need to
have an n plus one expression on the
bottom now the last thing we need to
deal with are the alternating signs it's
gonna alternate from positive to
negative it's a positive and so forth so
we can either use negative run to the N
or negative 1 to the n plus 1 which one
should we use now when n is 0 for the
first term we need to get a positive
sign a negative 1 to the 0 power is
positive 1 so we need to use this one
and so I'm going to write that here a
negative 1 to the N so this is the
Taylor series for the function Ln X
centered at C equal 1 and you can see
the X minus 1 term which tells us that
it's centered at C equals 1 for the sake
of practice let's go ahead and try
another example so find a Taylor series
for the function f of x equals e to the
X centered at C equals 3 so go ahead
pause the video and take a minute to try
this problem just like before let's make
a list of the function and its
derivatives so we have the function e 3x
the first derivative is going to be e to
the X as well as the second third and
the fourth
so all of the derivatives will be e to
the X now F of C which is basically f of
3 that's e to the 3 and that's can be
the same as f prime of 3 f double prime
of 3 and all of the derivatives
they will all be equal to e to the third
power now let's write out the function
so f of X is going to equal F of C plus
F prime of C times X minus C to the
first power plus the second derivative
times X minus C to the second power
divided by 2 factorial and then it's
going to be the third derivative times X
minus C to the third power over 3
factorial and then that's just going to
continue so our f of X is e to the X and
F of C or F of 3 that's e to the third
power F promisee is going to be the same
thing e to the third power the times X
minus C or CS 3 and then F double prime
of C is also going to be e to the third
power and then it's going to be times X
minus 3 to the second power over 2
factorial and then it's gonna be e to
the 3x minus 3 to the third power over 3
factorial now we need to write a general
power series that will give us what we
see here
so starting from zero going to infinity
we can see that the e to the third part
it doesn't change so that's pretty much
constant now the only part that changes
are the exponents and the factorials
therefore we need to represent those
numbers with something that contains the
letter n the only other part that
doesn't change is X minus 3 for every
term now when n equals 0 we have the e
to the third term when N equals 1 we're
going to get this term and then this is
for when N equals 2 and when N equals 3
and so notice that the N values matches
with the exponents and the factorials so
therefore we could say that this is X
minus 3 to the N power divided by n
factorial and this is the Taylor series
for the function e to the X centered at
C equal 3 let's move on to our next
example problem number 3 find the back
Laurent series for the function f of X
is equal to sine ax then we difference
between a Taylor series and the
Maclaurin series is that C equals 0 for
the Maclaurin series so that's why there
wasn't any C value given to you now the
first derivative which is the derivative
of sine that's going to be cosine and
then the second derivative is negative
sine X and then the derivative of
negative sine that's gonna be negative
cosine X and then the fourth derivative
is going to be the original sine X
function now the fifth derivative is the
same as the first and the sixth
derivative is the same as the second and
the pattern will repeat
so to evaluate f of 0 that's going to be
sine 0 which is 0 and then F prime of 0
cosine 0 is 1 and then f double prime of
0 that's negative sine 0 so that's 0 and
then for the third derivative it's going
to be negative cosine of 0 which is
negative 1 and for the fourth derivative
sine of 0 is 0 and so this is going to
be the same as the fifth derivative and
this is the 6 the 7th of 1/8
now let's find out the function that we
need in order to get the Maclaurin
series so f of X is going to equal f of
C but instead of F of C we're going to
replace C with 0 so it's gonna be f of 0
and then plus F prime of 0 times X minus
T's to the first power so that's X minus
0 to the first power which we can simply
write X to the first power and then it's
going to be the second derivative at 0
times x squared over 2 factorial plus
the third derivative at 0 times X cube
divided by 3 factorial and then that's
going to continue
so f of zero we could see that it's
equal to zero and then F prime of zero
that's equal to one so we're going to
have one X and then plus F double prime
of zero which is zero and then the third
derivative it's equal to negative one so
it's going to be negative x cube over 3
factorial and then the next term for the
fourth derivative is going to be zero
and then plus the fifth derivative so
it's going to be one times X to the
fifth over 5 factorial and then plus 0
and then minus for the seventh
derivative negative 1 times X to the 7
divided by 7 factorial
now let's simplify what we have so we
can get rid of all of the zeros so our
function which we can write as sine ax
that's equal to X which I'm going to
write as X to the first power divided by
1 factorial and then minus X to the
third power divided by 3 factorial plus
X to the fifth power over five factorial
minus X to the seventh power divided by
seven factorial and the series will go
on forever so now let's write a general
expression for that series so let's
start from 0 to infinity so when N
equals zero we need to get X to the
first power over 1 factorial and when n
is 1 we need to get 3 so let's write
down the sequence so the sequence of
numbers are 1 3 5 7 9 11 and so forth so
when n is 0 we get 1 when n is 1 we need
to get 3 when n is 2 we'll need to get 5
and the pattern will continue now what
we have is an arithmetic sequence and to
write the general formula for an
arithmetic sequence we can use this
equation so our a sub 1 term that's when
n is 1 that's can be 3 and the common
difference we could see that is 2 all of
the numbers are increasing by 2 and so
we have the expression a sub n is 3 plus
2 n minus 2 3 plus negative 2 that's 1
so we're going to get 2 n plus 1 and so
this is going to be X raised to the 2n
plus 1 divided by 2 n plus 1 factorial
since these numbers are the same so
therefore they share the same general
formula we just have a factorial symbol
at the bottom now the last thing we need
to deal with
are the alternating signs so the first
sign is positive when n is equal to zero
so therefore we need to use a negative 1
to the N power because negative 1 to the
0 power will give us positive 1 so this
is the Maclaurin series for sine X now
in this problem we're going to find the
Maclaurin series for cosine X using the
Maclaurin series for sine X so in the
last problem we saw that the Maclaurin
series for sine X was X minus X to the
3rd power divided by 3 factorial plus X
to the fifth power divided by 5
factorial minus X to the seventh power
divided by 7 factorial and this is going
to continue all the way to infinity
so what we're going to do is take the
derivative of both sides so on the left
side we have the derivative of sine
which will give us cosine X on the right
side the derivative of X is 1 the
derivative of x cubed is 3 x squared + 3
factorial we can write it as 3 times 2
times 1 and 2 times 1 is 2 factorial so
the next number is always 1 less than a
previous number when dealing with
factorials ok I'm not sure what just
happened here now the derivative of X to
the fifth power is 5 X to the fourth
power and 5 factorial I'm going to write
that as 5 times 4 factorial now the
derivative of X to the 7th power is
going to be 7 times X to the sixth power
and let's write 7 factorial as 7 times 6
factorial
now let's cancel the three we could
cancel the five and let's cancel the
seven so we're left with cosine X is 1
minus x squared divided by 2 factorial
plus X to the fourth over 4 factorial
minus X to the 6 divided by 6 factorial
now how can we represent this series
using summation notation now the first
thing I need to do is make some space
because I'm always short of it using
this board so what patterns do you see
now keep in mind when n is 0 we need to
get 1 when n is 1 we need to get the
exponents 2 and a factorial 2 and when n
is 3 we need to get 4 factorial I mean I
3 I skip two when n is 2 need to get 4
factorial and X to the fourth and then
when n is 3 we need to get 6 so notice
that the exponents and the factorials
are always 2 times
the N values so therefore this is going
to be X raise the 2 n divided by 2 n
factorial the last thing that we need to
talk about are the alternating signs so
the first sign is positive so just like
before we're going to use negative 1 to
the N power so this is the Maclaurin
series for cosine X now there's another
simple way of getting the same answer
I'm going to show it to you so we're
gonna start with this expression sine X
which we said was the series from 0 to
infinity and it was X to the 2n plus 1
times negative 1 to the N divided by t1
plus 1 factorial
so all we need to do in this example is
we just got to take the derivative of
both sides so the left side is going to
become cosine X now what about the
derivative for the right side so let's
rewrite the summation notation and we
need to realize that negative 1 to the N
is a constant 2 n plus 1 factorial
that's a constant so the only thing we
need to take the derivative of is X to
the 2n plus 1 and let's use the power
rule so based on the power rule the
derivative of X to the N is n X to the n
minus 1 so when you take the exponent
and move it to the front so that's gonna
be 2 n plus 1 times X and then we need
to subtract the exponent by 1 so let's
do that what is 2n plus 1 minus 1 so we
know that's gonna be 2n and then divided
by now this constant we're just going to
rewrite it so that's gonna be negative 1
to the N power now this constant will
remain but we want to cancel the 2n plus
1 so we're going to adjust the 2n plus 1
factor now recall that a factorial is 8
times 7 factorial and so we're gonna do
something like this so first we're going
to write the first number in this case
that's 2n plus 1 and then the next
number is going to be 2n plus 1 less one
to get the 7 is just 8 minus 1 so to get
the next number it's gonna be 2n plus 1
minus 1 which is 2n factorial
now we can cancel 2n plus 1 and this
gives us this answer as you can see so
that's the second way to get them back
Laurent series for cosine X
number five find the Maclaurin series
for cosine x squared so based on the
last problem we saw that the Maclaurin
series for cosine X was this expression
so it's negative 1 to the N times X
raised to the 2n divided by 2 and
factorial so if that's cosine X what can
we say about cosine squared all we need
to do is replace X with x squared so
this is going to be negative 1 to the N
times x squared raised to the 2n divided
by 2n factorial
now when you raise one exponent to
another you need to multiply so 2 times
2n is for n so therefore we can write
the series for this composite function
as negative 1 to the N times X raised to
the 4 n divided by 2n factorial and this
is the answer so that's the Maclaurin
series for cosine x squared that's what
you need to do if you have a composite
function now let's try this one number
six find the Maclaurin series for X
cosine X so how can we do this
if we call the Maclaurin series for
cosine X is this expression it's going
to be the power series of negative 1 to
the N times X raised to the 2n divided
by 2n factorial so all I need to do is
multiply X by X to the 2n and so this is
X to the first power therefore we need
to add 1 and chi'lan so the Maclaurin
series for X cosine X is going to be the
summation from 0 to infinity of negative
1 to the N times X raised to the 2n plus
1 over 2n factorial and that's all you
got to do for this problem now let's
find the Maclaurin series for the
function x squared e raised to the
negative x and this time use the data
table with the list of elementary
functions provided by your calculus
textbook now e to the X is equal to the
series from 0 to infinity X to the N
over N factorial so if that's easy X
what is e to the negative x so therefore
e to the negative x should be equal to
the series of negative x to the N over N
factorial so all I need to do is replace
X with negative X now what can we say
about negative X to the N negative X can
be written as negative 1 times X and
this is all affected by the exponent n
so let's distribute n so this becomes
negative 1 to the N times X to the N
so we're going to have x squared times
the series of a negative 1 to the N X to
the n divided by n factorial now at this
point we can multiply x squared by X to
the N so all we need to do is add the
exponents so 2 plus n we can write that
as n plus 2 and so this is going to be
the final answer so we have the series
from 0 to infinity negative 1 to the N
times X raised to the n plus 2 over N
factorial so that's equal to x squared e
to negative x and this is the final
answer let's work on one more problem
find the Maclaurin series for the
function f of x equals cosine squared so
what can we do with cosine squared of X
we can use the power reducing formula
for cosine squared which is 1/2 times 1
plus cosine 2x this comes from the
double angle formula of cosine 2x but
you rearrange it to solve for cosine
squared now we know that cosine X is
equal to this expression it's negative 1
to the N times X raised to the 2n over
2n factorial so therefore cosine 2 X is
going to be this expression it's going
to be negative 1 to the n times 2 X
raised to the 2n divided by 2 n
factorial so all you need to do is
replace X with 2 X
can leave your answer like this if you
want to and so this is the Maclaurin
series for cosine squared X